"Is Shrimp Bad for Cholesterol and Heart Disease?"
When people were randomized
to consume shellfish
or the same amount by protein
of meat, cheese, and eggs,
surprisingly, shrimp did not
lower their LDL cholesterol,
perhaps because shrimp is
so high in dietary cholesterol.
Shrimp is exceedingly low
in saturated fat,
like, 30 times less
than other meat,
but it has about
twice as much cholesterol,
which dietary guidelines
recommend we reduce in our diet
to as low as possible.
If people are given
the same amount of cholesterol
in the form of shrimp or eggs,
they get about the same rise
in LDL cholesterol,
which alone could increase our
lifetime risk of heart disease
by about 15%.
But there are a lot more people
eating two eggs a day
than, like, 11 ounces (310 g)
of shrimp a day.
And eating wild-caught
cold-water prawns,
a different species of shrimp,
doesn’t appear to budge
LDL cholesterol much at all.
Unfortunately,
about one in three shrimp
in the grocery store
is mislabeled,
so, it may be hard
to pick and choose.
There is another way
meat may contribute
to heart disease risk.
In certain areas
of the United States
and around the world,
getting bitten
by certain types of ticks
can make you allergic to meat.
In some parts of the U.S.
where the lone star tick
is endemic,
as many as 20% of people
have allergy-type antibodies
against meat
in their bloodstream.
But the prevalence
of clinically appreciated
allergic symptoms is thought
to be at least 10-fold less.
So, they’re sensitized to meat,
but when they eat it,
they don’t exhibit
any symptoms.
And because of that,
they continue to eat meat.
But what if that’s causing
inflammation inside their bodies
even if they don’t feel it?
And most concerningly,
what if it’s causing
more inflammation
in their artery walls?
Indeed, there were
significantly greater amounts
of athero-sclerotic plaque
in the individuals
who had detectable levels
of the anti-meat allergy
antibodies in their system.
So, people who consume
mammalian meat
appear to have
this chronic inflammation
in the walls
of their coronary arteries
that relates to this interaction
between this α-Gal component
of meat
and their anti-α-Gal antibodies
if they’ve been bitten
by a tick.
Those having a heart attack
had about a whopping
13 times higher likelihood
to having those antibodies,
providing strong
supportive evidence
for a clinically
important effect
of α-Gal sensitization
on the development
of coronary heart disease,
our leading cause of death,
and acute myocardial infarction,
or heart attack.
Okay, but wait a second.
If having an asymptomatic
food allergy
can so inflame our arteries,
what about other food allergies?
An allergy to shrimp is actually
the most common food allergy
in the United States,
affecting up
to 1 in 50 Americans,
but those are the people
who experience symptoms.
Might a shrimp allergy
actually be affecting more?
People with symptomatic
seafood allergies
tend to know they are allergic,
and know to just stay away
from shrimp.
But some people
with shrimp allergies
react differently.
Some have classic
allergy symptoms,
like breaking out in hives,
swelling,
and difficulty breathing,
but others develop symptoms
that manifest hours later-
gastrointestinal symptoms
like nausea,
abdominal cramps, diarrhea,
and vomiting.
So, some
shrimp-sensitive patients
just have this kind
of gastrointestinal upset.
But what about people
who are sensitized to shrimp,
and they don’t even know it
because they don’t
exhibit any symptoms?
In individuals without
symptomatic food allergy,
having allergy antibodies
in their blood
targeting some food
was considered
clinically irrelevant,
but that was before
those tick-induced meat
sensitization studies came out.
So, researchers looked to see
if having allergy antibodies
against other foods
was associated
with cardiovascular mortality,
and, indeed,
that’s just what they found.
From blood tests,
it appears about 1 in 25 people
is allergic to milk,
whether they know it or not.
And in these two large studies,
those who had
the milk sensitivity
had between 2
and nearly 4 times
the risk of dying
from cardiovascular disease,
but the worst
appeared to be shrimp.
6% of Americans,
about 1 in 17,
have anti-shrimp antibodies
in their blood,
whether they know it or not,
and those who do are 3.7 times
more likely to die
of cardiovascular disease,
but only if they eat shrimp.
Having anti-shrimp antibodies
doesn’t matter
if you don’t eat shrimp.
What about having a milk,
peanut, or egg sensitivity
but not eating those foods?
There were too few people
not eating those foods
to actually calculate it,
but enough people
don’t eat shrimp
that researchers could see
that having
anti-shrimp antibodies
only mattered
if you kept eating shrimp.
The thought
is that chronic oral exposure
to foods we have hidden
allergy antibodies for
can lead to chronic inflammation
that can manifest
in our arteries.
This definitely challenges
the current thinking
that these kinds
of food sensitivities
without overt allergy
is benign.